One time, though, I thought climbing a tree would lead to a great hiding spot,
ومع ذلك، ذات مرة اعتقدت بأن تسلق الشجرة سيقود إلى مخبإ عظيم،
but I fell and broke my arm.
ولكنني وقعتُ وكسرت يدي.
I actually started first grade with a big cast all over my torso.
بدأتُ بالفعل الصف الأول مع جبيرة كبيرة حول كل جذعي.
It was taken off six weeks later, but even then, I couldn't extend my elbow,
تم خلعها بعد ستة أسابيع، ولكن حتى في ذلك الوقت، لم أستطع مدَّ مرفقي،
and I had to do physical therapy to flex and extend it,
وكان عليَّ أن أقوم بعمل علاج طبيعي لتليينه وتمديده،
100 times per day, seven days per week.
100 مرة في اليوم، 7 أيام في الأسبوع.
I barely did it, because I found it boring and painful,
بالكاد قمت به، لأنني وجدته مملًا ومؤلمًا،
and as a result, it took me another six weeks to get better.
وكنتيجة لذلك، استغرق مني الأمر ستة أسابيع أخرى لأشعر بتحسن.
Many years later, my mom developed frozen shoulder,
وبعد عدة سنوات، عانت أمي من الكتف المتجمد،
which leads to pain and stiffness in the shoulder.
وهو يُحدث ألمًا وتشنجًا في الكتف.
The person I believed for half of my life to have superpowers
الشخص الذي اعتقدت على مدى نصف حياتي بأن لديه قدرات خارقة
suddenly needed help to get dressed or to cut food.
احتاج فجأةً إلى المساعدة ليلبس أو ليقطع الطعام.
She went each week to physical therapy, but just like me,
كانت تذهب كل أسبوع إلى العلاج الطبيعي، ولكنها بالضبط مثلي،
she barely followed the home treatment,
بالكاد اتبعتْ العلاج المنزلي،
and it took her over five months to feel better.
واستغرق منها الأمرُ أكثر من خمسة شهور لتشعر بالتحسن.
Both my mom and I required physical therapy,
كلانا، أنا وأمي، احتجنا للعلاج الطبيعي،
a process of doing a suite of repetitive exercises
وهو عملية القيام بمجموعة من التمارين المتكررة
in order to regain the range of movement lost due to an accident or injury.
بهدف استعادة نطاق الحركة الذي تم فقده نتيجة حادث أو إصابة ما.
At first, a physical therapist works with patients,
في البداية، يقوم الطبيب المعالج بالعمل مع المرضى،
but then it's up to the patients to do their exercises at home.
لكن بعدها عندها يكون عمل التمارين في المنزل على عاتق المرضى.
But patients find physical therapy boring, frustrating, confusing
لكن المرضى يشعرون بأن العلاج الطبيعي ممل ،ومخيب للأمل ،ومقلق
and lengthy before seeing results.
وطويل قبل أن يروا النتائج.
Sadly, patient noncompliance can be as high as 70 percent.
للأسف، نسبة عدم استجابة المرضى عالية وتصل إلى 70 بالمائة.
This means the majority of patients don't do their exercises
وهذا يعني أن معظم المرضى لا يقومون بتمارينهم
and therefore take a lot longer to get better.
ولذا يستغرقون وقتًا أطول للتعافي.
All physical therapists agree that special exercises
يتفق جميع أطباء العلاج الطبيعي على أن التمارين الخاصة
reduce the time needed for recovery,
تقلل الوقت اللازم للتعافي،
but patients lack the motivation to do them.
ولكن المرضى ينقصهم الحافز للقيام بها.
So together with three friends, all of us software geeks,
لذا وبصحبة ثلاثة من أصدقائي، جميعنا مهووسو برمجيات،
we asked ourselves,
سألنا أنفسنا،
wouldn't it be interesting if patients could play their way to recovery?
ألن يكون ممتعًا لو يستطيع المرضى اللعب حتى التعافي؟
We started building MIRA, A P.C. software platform
بدأنا ببناء "MIRA"، منصة برمجيات محوسبة
that uses this Kinect device, a motion capture camera,
تستخدم جهاز "Kinect" هذا، كاميرا تصوير حركي،
to transform traditional exercises into video games.
لتحويل التمارين التقليدية إلى ألعاب فيديو.
My physical therapist has already set up a schedule for my particular therapy.
قد حددت طبيبتي بالفعل جدولًا لعلاجي الخاص.
Let's see how this looks.
دعونا ننظر كيف يبدو هذا.
The first game asks me to fly a bee up and down
تطلب اللعبة الأولى مني تطيير نحلة إلى الأعلى والأسفل
to gather pollen to deposit in beehives,
كي تجمع اللقاح وتضعه في خلاياها،
all while avoiding the other bugs.
بينما تبتعد عن الحشرات الأخرى.
I control the bee by doing elbow extension and flexion,
أتحكم بالنحلة بواسطة تمديد وثني المرفق،
just like when I was seven years old after the cast was taken off.
بالضبط كما كنت في السابعة من عمري بعد خلع الجبيرة.
When designing a game, we speak to physical therapists at first
عند تصميم اللعبة، اعتدنا الحديث إلى الطبيب المعالج أولًا
to understand what movement patients need to do.
لفهم الحركة التي يحتاج المرضى إلى فعلها.
We then make that a video game
عندها نقوم بتحويلها إلى لعبة فيديو
to give patients simple, motivating objectives to follow.
لإعطاء المرضى أهداف محفزة لاتباعها.
But the software is very customizable,
ولكن البرنامج قابل جدًا للضبط،
and physical therapists can also create their own exercises.
ويستطيع الأطباء المعالجون أيضًا إنشاء تمارينهم الخاصة.
Using the software, my physical therapist
باستخدام البرنامج، قامت طبيبتي المعالجة
recorded herself performing a shoulder abduction,
بتصوير نفسها وهي تقوم بتبعيد الكتف،
which is one of the movements my mom had to do
وهي إحدى الحركات التي توجب على أمي القيام بها
when she had frozen shoulder.
عندما كانت تعاني من الكتف المتجمد.
I can follow my therapist's example on the left side of the screen,
بإمكاني اتباع مثال طبيبتي على الجانب الأيسر من الشاشة،
while on the right, I see myself doing the recommended movement.
بينما على الجانب الأيمن، أرى نفسي أفعل الحركة الموصى بها.
I feel more engaged and confident,
أشعر بأنني مشارك وواثق من نفسي بشكل أكبر،
as I'm exercising alongside my therapist
لأنني أتمرن بصحبة معالجي
with the exercises my therapist thinks are best for me.
بالتمارين التي يعتقد أنها الأفضل لي.
This basically extends the application for physical therapists
هذا ببساطة يوسع البرنامج بالنسبة للمعالجين
to create whatever exercises they think are best.
لإنشاء ما يرونها الأفضل من بين التمارين.
This is an auction house game for preventing falls,
هذه لعبة بيت المزاد، لتجنيب الوقوع،
designed to strengthen muscles and improve balance.
وهي مصممة لتقوية العضلات وتحسين التوازن.
As a patient, I need to do sit and stand movements,
كمريض، عليَّ القيام بحركات الجلوس والوقوف،
and when I stand up,
وعندما أقف،
I bid for the items I want to buy.
أزايد على أشياء أريد شرائها.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
In two days, my grandmother will be 82 years old,
في غضون يومين، ستبلغ جدتي 82 عامًا من عمرها،
and there's a 50 percent chance for people over 80
وثمة احتمال لـ 50% من الناس ممن تزيد أعمارهم عن 80 سنة
to fall at least once per year,
بأن يقعوا على الأقل مرة واحدة في السنة،
which could lead to a broken hip or even worse.
ما يمكن أن يؤدي إلى ورك مكسور أو أسوأ من ذلك.
Poor muscle tone and impaired balance are the number one cause of falls,
التناغم الضعيف في العضلات والتوازن الضعيف هي السبب الأول لعمليات السقوط،
so reversing these problems through targeted exercise
لذا فقلب هذه المشاكل من خلال تمرين هادف
will help keep older people like my grandmother
سيساعد في إبقاء كبار السن كجدتي
safer and independent for longer.
آمنين ومعتمدين على أنفسهم لمدة أطول.
When my schedule ends, MIRA briefly shows me
عندما ينتهي جدولي، يُظهر "MIRA" بوضوح لي
how I progressed throughout my session.
كيف تحسنت حالتي خلال جلستي العلاجية.
I have just shown you three different games
لقد أريتكم للتو ثلاث ألعاب مختلفة
for kids, adults and seniors.
للأطفال والبالغين وكبار السن.
These can be used with orthopedic or neurologic patients,
يمكن استخدام هذه الألعاب مع المرضى المشوهين أو مرضى الأعصاب،
but we'll soon have options for children with autism,
ولكننا قريبًا سنملك خيارات للأطفال المصابين بمرض التوحد
mental health or speech therapy.
وللصحة العقلية وعلاج النطق.
My physical therapist can go back to my profile
تستطيع طبيبتي العودة إلى ملفي
and see the data gathered during my sessions.
ورؤية البيانات التي تم جمعها خلال جلساتي.
She can see how much I moved, how many points I scored,
بإمكانها أن ترى كم تحركت وكم نقطة سجلت،
with what speed I moved my joints,
وبأي سرعة حركت مفاصلي،
and so on.
وهكذا.
My physical therapist can use all of this to adapt my treatment.
تستطيع طبيبتي استخدام كل هذا لتعديل علاجي.
I'm so pleased this version is now in use
أنا سعيد جدًا بأن هذه النسخة تُستخدم الآن
in over 10 clinics across Europe and the U.S.,
في أكثر من عشر عيادات في أرجاء أوروبا والولايات المتحدة،
and we're working on the home version.
ونحن نعمل على إعداد النسخة المنزلية منها.
We want to enable physical therapists to prescribe this digital treatment
نريد أن نمكِّن أطباء العلاج الطبيعي من وصف هذا العلاج الرقمي
and help patients play their way to recovery at home.
ومساعدة المرضى باللعب حتى التعافي في المنزل.
If my mom or I had a tool like this when we needed physical therapy,
إن امتلكتُ أنا أو أمي أداة كهذه عندما احتجنا إلى علاج طبيعي،
then we would have been more successful following the treatment,
عندها ربما اتبعنا العلاج بنجاح،
and perhaps gotten better a lot sooner.
وربما تحسنا بوقت أسرع.
Thank you.
شكرًا لك.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Tom Rielly: So Cosmin, tell me what hardware is this
توم: إذًا يا كوزمين، أخبرني ما هذا البرنامج
that they're rapidly putting away?
الذي ينقلونه بعيدًا وبسرعة؟
What is that made of, and how much does it cost?
ما الشيء الذي يُصنع منه وكم يكلف؟
Cosmin Milhau: So it's a Microsoft Surface Pro 3 for the demo,
كوزمين: إنه "ميكروسوفت سيرفيس برو 3" للتجربة،
but you just need a computer and a Kinect, which is 120 dollars.
ولكن تحتاج فقط إلى كمبيوتر و "Kinect"، وهو ما يبلغ ثمنه 120 دولار.
TR: Right, and the Kinect is the thing that people use for their Xboxes
توم: حسنًا، والـ "Kinect" هو ما يستخدمه الناس لأجهزة "Xbox" خاصتهم
to do 3D games, right?
لألعاب الـ "3D"، صحيح؟
CM: Exactly, but you don't need the Xbox, you only need a camera.
كوزمين: بالضبط، ولكنك لا تحتاج الـ "Xbox"، تحتاج فقط إلى كاميرا.
TR: Right, so this is less than a $1,000 solution.
توم: حسنًا، إذًا هذا حل بتكلفة أقل من 1,000 دولار.
CM: Definitely, 400 dollars, you can definitely use it.
كوزمين: بالتأكيد، 400 دولار، بإمكانك بالفعل أن تستخدمه.
TR: So right now, you're doing clinical trials in clinics.
توم: إذًا الآن، أنت تقوم بتجارب إكلينية في العيادات.
CM: Yes.
كوزمين: نعم.
TR: And then the hope is to get it so it's a home version
توم: إذًا فنأمل الحصول عليها وهكذا فهي نسخة منزلية
and I can do my exercise remotely,
وأستطيع القيام بتمريني عن بعد،
and the therapist at the clinic can see how I'm doing and stuff like that.
ويستطيع الطبيب المعالج في العيادة رؤية تقدمي وأشياء كهذه.
CM: Exactly.
كوزمين: بالضبط.
TR: Cool. Thanks so much. CM: Thank you.
توم: رائع. شكرًا جزيلًا. كوزمين: شكرًا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)